Guide to the New York University Department of History Oral History Class Collection OH.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I. Lower East Side Oral History Project Interviews, 1991-1994; 7 Linear Feet in 1 record carton, 4 media boxes, and 8 card catalog drawers; 0.75 Linear Feet in one record carton; 4 videocassettes (hi8); 4 videodiscs (dvd); 192 sound discs (cd); 133 audiocassettes
  - Rosen, Elizabeth Flynn, 1992 September 25; cuid492 (Box 1, Folder 81, Box 3, Cd 16)
    Elizabeth Flynn Rosen was born into a Jewish family in 1937 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Rosen's maternal grandparents immigrated to the United States from Poland and settled in the Lower East Side in the late 19th century. Her grandfather immigrated and established his pushcart business before his wife and daughter joined him in New York. Together, they opened a successful children's clothing factory. In 1908, her grandparents and mother moved to a brownstone building on Fourteenth Street in Manhattan.
    This interview was conducted on September 25, 1992 by Sharon B. Laist at Elizabeth Flynn Rosen's office at the Pierpont Morgan Library in Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers the immigration of Rosen's maternal grandparents and their life experiences in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Rosen describes how her maternal grandfather left his parent's home at 12 years old and traveled across Poland and Russia. She discusses her grandmother's success as a seamstress making children's pinafores and dresses in the Lower East Side and how this success led to the family's children's clothing factory. Rosen states that her grandfather started the concept of standard children's clothing sizes. She describes her grandfather as an idealist, who believed strongly in the capitalist system and the business opportunities it presents.
    Duration: 30:33
  - Rosenblatt, Marilyn Klein, 1991 September 29 (Box 1, Folder 82, Box 12, Cassette 36, Box 4, Cd 8)
    Marilyn Klein Rosenblatt was born into a Jewish family in 1934 in Brooklyn, New York. When she was four years old the family moved to the Far Rockaway neighborhood of Queens. Both of her parents were born in Brooklyn. Her grandparents immigrated to the United States from Russia, Hungary, and England. Rosenblatt attended Public School 39, Far Rockaway High School, and Queens College. She married in 1954 and had two daughters. She worked as a certified public accountant.
    This interview was conducted on September 29, 1991 by Ingrid Melhus and Renee Newman at Marilyn Klein Rosenblatt's home in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Rosenblatt's involvement with the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Rosenblatt discusses the lessons and activities in which she participated at the Henry Street Settlement, including taking piano lessons and singing in the chorus. She recounts performing with the Henry Street Settlement chorus at Carnegie Hall in Manhattan and on the radio program, We the People. She discusses patriotism in the United States after World War II and how this was reflected in the songs performed by the chorus. Rosenblatt sings and plays the piano during the interview.
    Duration: 1:07:26
  - Rosenfeld, Helen Tanenbaum, 1993 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 83, Box 13, Cassette 75A-75B, Box 5, Cd 10-11)
    Helen Tanenbaum Rosenfeld was born in 1911 in the Lower East Side neighborhood in Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she was one of five children. Her parents immigrated to the United States from the Polish region of Russia and owned a used furniture store in the Lower East Side. Rosenfeld attended Public School 1 and Washington Irving High School in Manhattan. The family moved to the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn when Goodman was a teenager.
    This interview was conducted on May 17, 1993 by Helen Goodman at Helen Tanenbaum Rosenfeld's apartment in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Goodman's childhood in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood in Manhattan and her family. Goodman recalls her childhood, including the family's apartments in the LES, the death of her grandfather, and her relationship with her four sisters. Goodman discusses her grandmother caring for her and her sisters and her grandmother's folk remedies. She discusses the ethnic composition of the sections of the LES in which she lived and the schools she attended, including Public School 1 and Washington Irving High School. She discusses her family's health, including her appendectomy after two of her sisters and her father had appendicitis.
    Duration: 2:11:06
  - Roth, Goldie Supsky, 1993 May 8 (Box 14, Cassette 76, Box 1, Folder 84, Box 5, Cd 12)
    Goldie Supsky Roth was born into a Jewish family in 1910 in Poland. Her mother died when Roth was four weeks old. Roth lived with her grandmother until her father remarried and decided to immigrate to the United States (US) in 1914. The family settled in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her father owned a factory manufacturing ladies' skirts. In 1916, Roth went to live with her aunt and uncle in the LES. Roth attended Public School 42, Seward Park Junior High School, and Seward Park High School in the LES. She married in 1929 and moved to the Borough Park neighborhood of Brooklyn.
    This interview was conducted on May 8, 1993 by Helen Goodman in Brooklyn, New York. The interview covers Goldie Supsky Roth's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and her family. Roth describes her family's apartment on Madison Street in the LES, including the appliances and amenities in the apartment. She discusses moving to Clinton Street in the LES in 1916 to live with her aunt, uncle, and two cousins and describes their apartment. She discusses activities and classes in which she participated at the Educational Alliance and Hester Park in the LES, including Yiddish classes and summer camp. She discusses her early life in Poland, her immigration to the United States when she was four years old, and the fact that she was raised by her aunt in the LES. She discusses customs and traditions in the LES, including ice and coal deliveries and around local and national elections. Other topics include her education, vermin in the LES, evictions in the LES, and social activities she would participate in with her friends and her husband.
    Duration: 38:17
  - Rothstein, Augusta Agatstein, 1993 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 85, Box 14, Cassette 77, Box 5, Cd 13)
    Augusta Agatstein Rothstein was born in 1925 in New York, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had two sisters and four step-siblings. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Austria and worked as a painter and decorator. He worked for the Works Progress Administration during the Great Depression before opening his own painting business. He married three times and had four children from his two other marriages. Her mother immigrated to the US from Russia and managed the household. Rothstein attended Public School 63.
    This interview was conducted on July 15, 1993 by Goldie Gold in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Augusta Agatstein Rothstein's early life and family. Rothstein describes her family's apartment and their neighbors in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She discusses her orthodox Jewish upbringing throughout the interview, including her attendance at services at a synagogue and Hebrew school in addition to public school. She describes her parents including her father's three marriages, his children from his other marriages, his immigration to the United States, and his work as a painter and decorator for the Works Progress Administration. She discusses social activities in which her family participated and customs in her household and neighborhood.
    Duration: 47:25
  - Rubin, Sol, 1993 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 86, Box 14, Cassette 78, Box 5, Cd 14)
    Sol Rubin was born in 1916 in Poland. He immigrated to the United States with his parents and siblings in 1934. They settled in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. His family was Jewish and he had three siblings. Rubin worked as a bookbinder, photographer, and filmmaker. He was a member of the Workmen's Circle. He married and had two daughters.
    This interview was conducted on June 10, 1993 by Helen Goodman at her home in New York, New York. The interview covers Sol Rubin's life in New York after his immigration in 1934. Rubin describes the apartments in which he lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. He recounts the differences between life in a small town in Poland and life in New York. He discusses cultural activities in which he participated in New York, including a poetry club and photography club at the Educational Alliance in the LES. He describes the people and stores in the LES in the 1930s and 1940s and discusses the changes in the neighborhood at the time of the interview. He recounts attending political events he attended and photographed, including Vito Marcantonio. He recalls his memories of Pearl Harbor and World War II, including receiving his draft letter in 1941, his experiences in the US Army in northern Africa between 1942 and 1945.
    Duration: 1:22:34
  - Safian, Harriet Cohen, 1993 August 3 (Box 14, Cassette 79, Box 1, Folder 87, Box 5, Cd 15)
    Harriet Cohen Safian was born in 1921 in the Jewish Maternity Hospital in Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had two siblings. Her parents immigrated to the United States from the Polish region of Russia, her father from Siemiatycze and her mother from Horodetz. Her father was a metal worker and owned a fixtures store, and her mother managed the household. The family lived in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan. Safian attended Public School 2, Corlears Junior High School, and Seward Park High School in the LES. She attended Hunter College in Manhattan and Brooklyn College in Brooklyn. She received her master's degree in social work from Smith College in Northampton, Massachusetts. She worked as a social worker. She married and had children. She was a member of the Workmen's Circle, Branch 1052 in Manhattan and the Service Employees International Union, Local 1199.
    This interview was conducted on August 3, 1993 by Helen Goodman at an unspecified location. The interview covers Harriet Cohen Safian's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and her working life. Safian describes her family's apartment on Madison Street in the LES, including the layout, the appliances and amenities in the apartment, and the living arrangements. She discusses her brother, including his paralysis from poliomyelitis, his education, and the fact that she saw him as a role model. She discusses her parents, their immigration experiences, and their work in the United States. She discusses her education, social activities in which she would participate in the neighborhood and at the Educational Alliance in the LES, and customs in the LES around local and national elections. She discusses her work as a social worker, including the hospitals at which she worked in New York, her membership in the Service Employees International Union, Local 1199, and social programs she managed and helped institute at the hospitals at which she worked. Other topics include family pets, her membership in the Workmen's Circle in Manhattan, and her husband.
    Duration: 1:12:58
  - Salwen, Irving, 1994 February 22 (Box 14, Cassette 101, Box 1, Folder 88, Box 6, Cd 1)
    Irving Salwen lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York from the age of seven. Salwen's father immigrated to the United States from an unspecified European country and owned a wholesale business. Salwen owned a wholesale business on Orchard Street in the Lower East Side.
    This interview was conducted on February 22, 1994 by Karen Baker at an unspecified location. The audio recording is difficult to understand as the voices are muffled. Irving Salwen's wife and grandson interject throughout the interview. Salwen discusses his devotion to his father and the family wholesale business. He recalls Orchard Street being very dirty, and lined with garbage and rodents during his childhood. Salwen talks about taking violin lessons while he was in high school and plays the violin at the end of the interview.
    Duration: 01:17:08.
  - Saperstein, Judith Epstein, 1993 May 13 (Box 14, Cassette 80, Box 1, Folder 89, Box 5, Cd 16)
    Judith Epstein Saperstein was born in 1922 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had one brother. Her father immigrated to the United States (US) from Russia and owned a newspaper stand. Her mother immigrated to the US from the Lithuanian region of Russia and managed the household. Saperstein attended Public School 188 in the LES. She married in 1942 and had three children. After her marriage she lived on Attorney Street and moved to the Seward Park Houses in 1960.
    This interview was conducted on May 13, 1993 by Annette Franklin at Judith Epstein Saperstein's apartment in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Saperstein's early life in the LES and her family. Throughout the interview Saperstein describes the apartments in which she lived in the LES and her extended family. She describes her family's apartments on Cannon and Norfolk Streets, the living arrangements in the apartments, and how the family negotiated privacy for themselves. She describes her first apartment with her husband on Attorney Street in the LES and her happiness over having a shower. She discusses the chores she and her mother conducted in the house and discusses a laundry service her mother used. She discusses her father's newsstand, in particular her responsibilities at the stand and the fact that her family's life revolved around the business. She discusses her parents, including their immigration experiences and their leisure activities, including the Yiddish theatre. She discusses her maternal uncles, their leisure activities, and the fact that they supported Saperstein's family. Saperstein discusses her children, their educations, their careers, and their families. She describes her apartment in the Seward Park Houses in the LES. Other topics include her mother's illness and later life, her family's traditions around Jewish holidays, and customs in the LES.
    Duration: 1:34:20
  - Schatsky, Julius, 1992 November 13 (Box 11, Cassette data_value_missing_73cc51687715dfe873c087795b71b14f, Box 1, Folder 90, Box 3, Cd 17-18)
    Julius Schatsky was born in 1924 into a Jewish family in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Schatsky's father was a junk man who collected and sold metal. Schatsky attended Public School 147 (PS147) and attended Camp Henry in the Lower East Side. He was a member of several clubs that met at the Henry Street Settlement and Educational Alliance in the Lower East Side. He attended Murray Hill Vocational School and later worked for the Federal Security Agency between 1947 and 1956.
    This interview was conducted on November 13, 1992 by Aimee Kaplan at the home of Julius Schatsky's younger brother, Sam Schatsky, in Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Julius Schatsky's childhood and life in a Jewish household in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Schatsky recalls living in three different apartments on Henry Street. He describes one of the family's apartments, including a bathtub in the kitchen with a removable cover that functioned as additional counter space, and the shared bathroom in the hallway. He speaks fondly of his many neighborhood friends and the street games they played together. He remembers joining the Cub Scouts at the Educational Alliance in the Lower East Side and attending a summer picnic sponsored by the Henry Street Settlement in White Plains, New York.
    See also: Sam Schatsky's interview.
    Duration: 01:52:26
  - Schatsky, Sam, 1992 November 23 (Box 11, Cassette 10A-10B, Box 1, Folder 91, Box 3, Cd 19-20)
    Sam Schatsky was born in 1928 into a Jewish family in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Sam and his brother, Julius Schatsky, attended programs and clubs ran by the Educational Alliance and the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side.
    This interview was conducted on November 23, 1992 by Aimee Kaplan at Sam Schatsky's home in Manhattan, New York. The majority of the interview covers Schatsky's childhood and life in a Jewish household in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. Schatsky recalls moving from 253 Henry Street to 254 Henry Street and his opinion that the latter was more modern because it had a bathroom inside the apartment rather than in the hallway. He describes feeling a sense of inferiority when he would accompany his mother on her trips to the welfare office during the 1930s and 1940s. Schatsky states that the street and the Henry Street Settlement in the Lower East Side provided space for the neighborhood children to play together. He also discusses his philosophical opinions about being Jewish, the importance of friendship, and his love for New York City. See also Julius Schatsky's interview.
    Duration: 02:04:19
  - Schmidt, Jacqueline, 1993 September 8 (Box 14, Cassette 81, Box 1, Folder 92, Box 5, Cd 17)
    Jacqueline Schmidt was born in 1937 in New York, New York. Her family was Catholic and she had one brother. Her parents were both born in the United States. Her father worked as a systems analyst and her mother managed the household. Her parents divorced when she was eight years old and both of them remarried. Between 1949 and 1955, she lived with her grandfather on Third Street in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. When she entered high school, she moved to the Woodside neighborhood of Queens to live with her father. Schmidt attended Public School 25 in the LES, an unspecified junior high school in Woodside, and Central Commercial High School in Manhattan. She worked as a secretary and was married.
    This interview was conducted on September 8, 1993 by Helen Goodman in Brooklyn, New York. About half of the second track of the recording is blank. The interview covers Jacqueline Schmidt's early life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan and her family. Schmidt describes apartments in which she lived and in which her family members lived in the LES, including the neighborhoods, the amenities and utilities in the apartments, and living arrangements in the apartments. She discusses living with her grandfather in order to care for him between 1949 and 1955, and describes the apartment in which they lived on Third Street in the LES and the chores for which she was responsible. She describes the apartment and neighborhood in which her mother and stepfather lived on Avenue C at Sixth Street in the LES and the different pushcarts that were outside their apartment. She discusses traditions in her family around Easter and Christmas, the fact that Czechoslovakian and Italian traditions were combined, and her favorite traditions for each holiday. She explains the reasons why she moved between family members, first living with her mother and stepfather and then her grandfather in the LES, moving to the Woodside neighborhood of Queens to live with her father, and returning to the LES to live with her mother when she attended high school. She discusses her education and after school activities in which she participated, in particular basketball. She discusses her parents' divorce, their second marriages, and the fact that she moved between their households. She describes her relationship with her parents and activities they would do together. Other topics include a comparison of life in the LES between the 1940s and at the time of the interview, one of her maternal aunts who performed in a carnival, her extended family members, and her memories Yiddish theatres in the LES.
    Duration: 1:34:38
    Children of divorced parents -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews.; Families -- New York (State) -- New York -- Anecdotes.
  - Schneeweiss, Samuel, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    Samuel Schneeweiss was born in 1919 in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. He had two sisters. His parents immigrated to the United States from Austria-Hungary and owned a grocery store in the LES. Schneeweiss attended Public Schools 174 and 4, Forsyth Junior High School, and Seward Park High School. He received his bachelor's degree from New York University (NYU) and his law degree from the NYU School of Law in Manhattan. He was a member of the Henry Street Oldtimers at the Henry Street Settlement in the LES and helped establish the Henry Street Settlement Federal Credit Union.
    The interviewer and location of this interview are unknown. The interview was conducted in 1991. The audio recording for this interview is missing. The interview covers Samuel Schneeweiss's life in the Lower East Side (LES) neighborhood of Manhattan, New York and his family. Schneeweiss discusses his parents, their immigration experiences, and their working lives. He discusses his education and the schools he attended in the LES. He describes social and leisure activities in which he would participate, particularly at settlement houses in the LES. He discusses his relationship with his parents, the fact that his father did not pressure him to participate in specific activities, and the importance his mother placed on education. He discusses the importance of the Henry Street Settlement in his life, activities in which he would participate at the Settlement, his memories of Helen Hall, and his participation in the establishment of the Henry Street Settlement Federal Credit Union in 1973. He discusses the Henry Street Oldtimes, members of the group, and programs and activities the group supports at the Henry Street Settlement.
  - Seltzer, Zelda Lampert, 1993 May 25 (Box 14, Cassette 82, Box 1, Folder 94, Box 5, Cd 18)
    Zelda Lampert Seltzer was born in 1923 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan, New York. Her family was Jewish and she had four siblings. Her parents immigrated to the United States from Poland. Her father worked as a presser in the garment industry and her mother managed the household. Seltzer attended Public School 15 and Seward Park High School in the LES. She graduated from the City University of New York. She worked as a bookkeeper, an accountant, and a high school teacher. She belonged to the Workmen's Circle, Branch 1076.
    This interview was conducted on May 25, 1993 by Goldie Gold in Manhattan, New York. The interview covers Zelda Lampert Seltzer's early life and family. Seltzer describes the apartments in which her family lived in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. She recalls her family always having a boarder staying in their apartment and describes the crowded living arrangements in the apartment. She describes her parents throughout the interview, including their backgrounds in Poland and interests, their immigration to the United States, her father's interest in politics, and the impact of her father's poor health on her family. She describes her mother's chores in the house and the after-school jobs she and her siblings held. She recounts jobs she held during and after college, including bookkeeper, accountant, and high school teacher. She discusses her and her siblings' relationship with their parents and discipline in the family.
    Duration: 1:12:33
  - Shapiro, Norman, 1994 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 95, Box 15, Cassette 102, Box 6, Cd 2)